In studio with us, executive vice
president and general manager Nick
Cacerio. Nick, congratulations on the
draft. How's it going,
>> fellas? Great to see you. It's been a
while.
>> Well, we have a lot of questions for you
about the draft and then some. Let's
start off with Keelin Rutled and the
offensive line in general, Nick, because
you added a lot this off season in the
draft and free agency and your
resignings as well.
>> Yeah, that was a key part of it kind of
in the front end there with the
resignings of Ed. um that was a big part
of it and resigning of Trent as well who
both played pretty good football for us
there last year that made some
acquisitions there in the free agent
process with the signing of Wyatt and
Evan Brown as well. So felt there's four
players with, you know, NFL experience
that have played and or started a number
of games. Um, in the draft, we were able
to acquire, you know, a few more players
to add to that mix. Um, you mentioned
with Rutled Air, the first pick. Um, and
then Fabi there in the fourth round. Um,
two good football players who have
really good traits, good makeup, the
right mentality, the right mindset who
collectively, organizationally you felt
pretty strongly about.
>> A, you saved the draft party. Thank you.
>> Everybody wanted the draft party to be a
hit. You made it a hit. You also said
this after the draft. I I said the same
thing, too. So, I want to get your
thoughts on it. You said after the
draft, you're like, I went up two spots.
It's not really trading up. You didn't
really quote unquote I mean,
technically, you did, but you really
didn't. But you did go up two spots.
What was it that you felt like going up
two spots was was doing to make sure you
got Keelin? What was kind of moving up a
little bit there, Nick, in the first?
Yeah, like we've talked a lot of these
moves are just about positioning and you
feel like, well, we think we need to get
to a certain point just to make sure
that we acquire the player and not run
the risk potentially of losing him. You
don't know exactly what's going to
happen, but we just felt we had to make
a small subtle move to get in a position
where we could draft the player who we
felt was probably going to go in about
that range. As we got a little bit
closer to the draft, it started to
materialize. It was probably in that 25
to 40ish sort of range whether or not he
would have made it to 38. So then it was
like, "All right, well, if this is a
player that we like and we want, if we
have to make a small subtle move, then
let's investigate and see what our
options are."
>> And along those lines, when Friday night
hits and Kaden McDonald, you like him,
picks are starting to go and you have to
know when to pull the trigger on that
deal, but you got your guy.
>> Sure. Similar to the the Rutler's
discussion, really just make a a small
subtle move to kind of get in position.
We felt like at some point he was
probably going to go pretty quickly that
night. he wasn't going to last very long
and you know he was probably one of the
better players that was still available
at that time. Therefore, we made the
move that we did uh you know had Kaden
in here uh at some point in the in the
process. Had a really good season last
year really the most extensive uh play
time of his career. Had an opportunity
did a good job in coach Patric Coach
Patricia's system there. Um he made I
want to say like 30 plus assists and
then another 30 total tackles or solo
tackles. So, you're talking about a
player that had made 60 tackles from an
interior defensive tackle position. Not
too dissimilar to some of the things
that Tommy showed during the season for
us. So, a good football player that's
young, that's strong, and has some
traits that we feel fit our defense.
>> Nick, on Friday morning and afternoon,
as you lead up to Friday evening, and
you're going to make that pick, you're
sitting, I think, what, six picks away
from the first pick of the draft. How do
you guys kind of handle that going into
it? Do you do, you know, some kind of
simulations to see what might happen in
those picks? How do you guys kind of
handle that time between Thursday
night's end of the draft and then
Friday's start?
>> For sure. It's a little bit of
everything. So, look at those first
eight to 10 picks, let's say, because we
were picking 38 through your point.
Those first eight to 10 picks, who is
most likely to get drafted? What are
some of the teams that may have needs at
certain positions? Where are we on
certain players? Who's a cohort of
players that we like? Okay, who who do
we feel comfortable drafting? So those
are the things that we're discussing
throughout the course of the day. And if
we have to do a little bit more work or
diligence, do one last checkpoint, then
that's what we go through. So it's
pretty fluid. We're kind of preparing
for that pick and then once you get past
that pick, then you're preparing for the
rest of the evening there. Um at the
time, I think we were scheduled to pick
three times. We only end up picking
twice because we made the subtle move up
for McDonald. Um but we were still kind
of playing it out there even into the
third round. Even though we didn't have
a pick, we were still looking if there
was an opportunity that presented itself
that made sense, then we would consider
it and and ultimately make the right
decision with Klene. And great
interview, by the way. It was wonderful
to have him on Friday night. How hard is
it to make that kind of decision, this
guy, this is the guy we want right here.
We got to go get him. A lot of tight
ends to choose from. It's not later in
the draft, but it's, you know, second
round, getting late in the second round.
How do you make that pick, Nick?
>> Yeah, for sure. He was a player that we
had kind of liked from the beginning of
the process and kind of till the end. We
were probably pretty consistent in how
we felt about the player. And the
reality is we were at 59 or wherever we
were picking. There was a few trade
scenarios that were actually on the
table for us to move back and we were
close to making a trade to move back. We
felt like if we've moved back a few
spots, still had a shot to get possibly
get the player. The trades kind of fell
through. So we've always talked at some
point if you don't have a trade then you
just got to be ready to pick. So,
whoever you're going to pick, so we
picked Marlin because that was a player
that we had kind of teed up as the next
player.
>> Nick, I heard this guy, I think it was
on McAfee show maybe today.
>> Yeah.
>> He said, "Toughness and physicality win
this league." Physicality, I think you
can see on film. How tough is it to
actually discern toughness in an
individual as you're scouting him? Nick,
>> it's difficult, but there are things
that you can look for. You can look at
how he finishes. Does he play to the
whistle? However many snaps there are in
a game, 65, 70 snaps. What's his playing
style? What's his mentality? What's his
mindset? Does he take a play off? Is he
consistent all the way across the board?
And then when you visit with the player,
you get a sense and a feel for their
personality. Do they have some edge? Do
they have some grit? Do they have some
toughness? What's important to them?
What do they prioritize? That's the way
you kind of piece it all together. It's
not as if you can just open up a book
and say there's toughness. You have to
do some digging. And then you have to
rely on sources, talk to coaches, talk
to teammates, get their opinion of the
player, see what they happen to think,
and then create the profile and then say
ultimately in the end, we feel he has
those qualities that we cover here.
>> Nick, not everybody has this in common,
but we look at Woodads, we look at Bond,
these guys were at their schools their
entire careers, and then a couple of
others, they transferred up, they
upgraded in the level of play in college
football. How important or pertinent is
that kind of thing? Yeah, it speaks to
their profile. Those individuals maybe a
little bit different than some other
individuals. We don't penalize anybody
for what they do or have not done, but
in those two particular cases, they
probably had opportunities to go
elsewhere. And honestly, it speaks to
the program. I mean, Davo has run one of
the best best most consistent programs
for as long as he's been there. Um, and
coach O'Brien came into BC. I'm sure
Lewis had an opportunity, maybe wasn't
sure what was going to happen because he
was there with the previous staff and
then he made a decision to stay and then
he had two of his most productive
seasons of his career in the last two
seasons, including I think he broke the
single season reception record for
Boston College this past year. So, in
the end, the player has to make an
individual choice about what they feel
is best for their situation. Nick, one
of the things that both you and Demo
talked about, hey, look, we're going to
find really good football players, but
the person matters. And it feels like
this draft after, you know, Brooke would
do an interview or Mark would do an
interview with a player, you listen to
the interview and you go, "Oh, okay. I
get it." Like, I get why because we
don't have that opportunity to meet him.
You guys obviously do. Why has that
become such a a mantra for for this
particular organization and team, Nick?
Well, I think as in the end, you're
going to win with people and you're
going to win with toughness and you
understand you're going to face some ups
and downs and you're going to face some
adversity. So, who are the players that
can kind of handle that without sort of
riding the wave and just be consistent
day after day, week after week, month
after month, because that's what this
league is about ultimately. So, it's 17
opportunities. You get one each week and
whatever happens the previous week, we
have to put that aside and then you have
to be able to transition into the next
week. So mentality, mindset, just their
overall thought process, their
intentionality about how they how they
approach their work is ultimately going
to be um really really important. But
how difficult is that to research
because as we're talking to some of
these players, Nick, it sounds like they
were all coached up to say some similar
things. Not all of the content, but a
lot of similar things. And I can vouch
they were not coached by PR. They jumped
right on the line and we talked to them
fresh. So what about that?
>> Well, I think that was our overall
impression of the players when we
interacted with them. So whether it was
the information we received from the
coaches, whether it was the interview we
did with them either at the senior bowl,
at the combine, or if we happen to have
them in the building, we probably
arrived at the same conclusion. So we in
the end, the players are who they are.
We're not going to force them to be
something that they're not. So to your
point, Mark, it's not easy to do, but
you have to have enough discipline and
conviction to say these are the things
that are important. Who are the players
that have those qualities? and as best
you can try to go out and identify them
and if you have an opportunity to add
them to the team then you add them to
the team.
>> Nick, we've talked about this a little
bit before but it felt like it was a
talking point for a lot of people
afterwards and and we talked about it a
little bit during the draft and that was
the NIL and the transfer portal impact
on this particular draft and maybe
trends we're seeing over the last couple
years as NIL and transfer portal have
become even more important. Did you see
changes kind of in in what might be
available on on day three or maybe even
late on day two because guys decided to
stay maybe for an extra year or the
player you found on day three maybe a
little more polished because they did
stay an extra year because they made
some NIO money.
>> Yes. It goes both ways. So as I think
there was 67 underassman. 60 of them
were drafted. There were very few of
those underassmen that were drafted. I
want to say after the third round I want
to say it was like four or five or
something like that. So what has
happened is just the pool and volume of
overall players has shrunk relative to
underassman. So then you transition to
this next group of players and then
we're going back to okay he was at this
program then he transferred what was the
reason that he transferred. So you don't
penalize a player for moving or nil.
That's the reality of college football.
So our job is just to understand it and
understand the dynamics surrounding the
player and ultimately just make the find
the players that we feel are are the
right fits for the Texans. Nick, can you
give us something on Wade Woodazz and
Aiden Fischer, the linebackers?
Different rounds, but what do they have
in common? And how happy is Frank Ross
about these picks?
>> Yeah, I'd say he's pretty happy,
especially with the Woodazz pick. I say
they're they're different, but they're
similar. Woodazz is a, you know, 6'3,
235 lb former safety that kind of moved
down to call it a hybrid position. Kind
of played detached from the formation,
but he's a linebacker. And I'd say that
type of body type is a more prevalent on
rosters and you're starting to see it on
coverage units some of these bigger
bodies factor in because you're dealing
with shorter spaces. Um, and he was kind
of a sideline to sideline player. He's
got good straight line speed, good
toughness, very highly thought of in the
Clemson program. And then with Aiden,
I'd say you see a very uh highly u
instinctive, aware, productive player
with very good toughness. He's not as
big as Woodaz. I mean WoodZ is 63 235.
Aiden 6 foot 230, you know, 235,
probably a little bit closer to like a
Jake Hansen type of build.
>> Um, transfer up player. He was with
coach Sig at at James Madison and there
was, I don't know, 15, 20, 25 players
that went from JMU to Indiana and he was
a part of that. But leadership,
toughness, I think he was a captain, was
essentially the the quarterback of the
defense. Um, and you see that in his
play.
>> Nick, one of the questions I got a
couple weeks ago, and I thought it was
an interesting one. I was meeting with
the the ticket department. They asked me
about a a winning program player, you
know, a guy that's played for for an
Indiana. And immediately when Aiden
Fischer was drafted, the first thing
came to my mind was that guy came over
from James Madison. Indiana became
really good defensively. He was the
leader of that. Then they win a national
championship. He's the leader of that.
How much does winning or being a part of
a winning program matter in a sense?
Because I'm sure over the years you
drafted somebody from a 111 football
team and they've played well for you.
you drafted players from national
championship teams, they probably
haven't. What does winning and how does
that kind of play into a player's draft
pick?
>> Sure. Winning matters and even go back
to high school, there's some players
that are affiliated with very successful
high school programs. So, they have an
understanding of what winning looks like
and what is required of winning.
Understanding it's not going to be easy.
So, it's certainly a part of the
calculus that goes into it. So when
you're around winning, when you're
around like-minded people, then you're
going to hopefully see some of the same
things and maybe some of the players
that we have here because in the end,
our goal is to win. So who are the
players that are going to help us win?
Do they have the right mentality? Do
they know what it looks like and they're
going to apply themselves to ultimately
get to that end point?
>> So USC a little bit of a theme last
three drafts with
>> certainly appears that Ramsey getting
selected. Yes. And how much does that
help though that you're familiar with
what it looks like in that program and
Ramsay had played with JRock
>> for sure. And they've actually had some
turnover on the coaching staff. So
you're just kind of because even with
Kamari, he played safety in 24 and then
they moved him down to a little bit more
of a nickel position this past year.
Probably a little bit better safety than
he is a nickel, but good size, very
smart, very instinctive, different, but
like Fiser in that respect. You can kind
of see his awareness and how he plays.
Um, you know, he was a player. Our
grades were consistent throughout the
process. We had a good Zoom discussion
with him when our coaches visit with him
and kind of confirmed some of the things
that that we thought, but a good
football player from a good program. Um,
no question about it.
>> Nick, as you went through this draft
process this year, six draft, and you've
been very successful with the draft, so
you don't want to get away from that
obviously, but were there was there
anything that you kind of incorporated
this year that maybe you hadn't done as
much in the past as you evaluated
players? Yeah, I think we kind of always
look at some of our processes and there
are some tweaks and adjustments that we
can make. I'd say it's more subtle
changes and tweaks than not a complete
overhaul. But if there's a tool we can
incorporate is there's some other idea
or maybe a different avenue that helps
our player evaluation process
>> then if it makes sense then we'll try to
incorporate it. But the core of it I
would say has remained the same. You
want to understand the player, get their
background, what's their football
character, what's their football
intelligence, their competitiveness,
their overall toughness, evaluate the
player on film, and then there's some
other, I would say, tools and components
that you can use that go into evaluating
a player.
>> Will Bond have a quote easier time
adjusting to this offense having played
at BC? Are there some similarities there
with the two offenses?
>> There'll probably be some carryover
relative to the terminology. It's not
like apples to apples, but there'll
probably be some things that carry over,
but ultimately like we might call it a
little bit different, but it might mean
the same thing. So again, a lot of these
players are going to have to translate.
They're learning a new language,
>> right?
>> Here's what I understand this as last
year. You're doing the same thing.
You're just calling it something
different. So that that's really where
the adjustment takes place.
>> So undrafted free agent process goes on
after the draft. That's all done and you
get in your vehicle to drive home and
it's kind of the first time maybe you
could take a breath for a while. What
are you kind of thinking as you're
driving home, leaving out of here, you
can kind of have the draft in the
rearview mirror and start getting ready
for, you know, rookie mini camp, but
that's for a couple weeks, you kind of
get a breath. What's kind of your
thought as you're leaving out of here?
>> Yeah, it's where are we right now? What
else could we do or what do we if
there's anything we need to do and just
kind of take inventory, understand like
you said, we have the undrafted players
coming in. At some point, we'll probably
have some like try out or workout type
players as a part of that, like who fits
that profile. And then we're starting to
shift here really from the coaching
standpoint to focus on our players to on
the field. They've been in the weight
room. They've been training. We're kind
of going through phase one. So you just
kind of it's a subtle okay
quick breath.
>> Y
>> where are we? What else do we need to
do? And what opportunities externally
are still out there that might be able
uh might be able to enhance our team.
>> So with the undrafteds, that's kind of a
recruitment process, right? you have to
lure them in, for lack of a better way
of putting it. Is that still sort of a
best athlete available? Wait a minute,
we can get this guy or we're looking to
fill certain spots maybe where we want
more depth.
>> It's probably a little bit more numbers
based like if we know we're going to
need x number of players at a certain
position. We're still we're looking for
volume, but you still don't want to
sacrifice the things that we talked
about earlier. you don't necessarily
sacrifice that because
>> how they practice, their work ethic,
their competitiveness, ultimately that's
going to show up where they are on the
talent matrix or the skill matrix. Okay,
that's a part of it. You're not just
going to kind of throw caution to the
wind and just say, "Well, we're going to
take that guy even though it was like
traits or makeup or maybe below the
line." So, it's case by case. Certain
positions we're going to bring in more
players than others. Other positions a
little bit more targeted and hopefully
we've had a touch point with that player
throughout the course of the spring. So
when you do pick up the phone, it's not
the first time you've talked to Joe
Smith and said, "Hey, we'd love for you
to come to the Texans." And he says,
"Coach, like I haven't heard from you at
all." So there's a little bit of
recruiting that goes on ahead of time.
In the event that this happens, we would
like you to be a part of it. And if they
have a better opportunity somewhere
else, they feel like that what's best
for them, no problem. Then we move on to
the next player.
>> Some point earlier this week, Nick, I
happened to see a video. I think maybe
Seth put it up there. It was Keelin
playing basketball and you watch it,
you're like, "Dang, that's a good drop
step." Like, I would not want to play
pickup ball against that guy. We talked
about this a little bit, but in this
group in particular, how did playing of
other sports
matter for the guys that you brought in?
I mean, Marlin had played soccer and
then he comes here and he plays American
football, but how did playing a second
or a third sport did you see kind of
manifest itself in the guys?
>> It's always good to see when they can
play multiple sports. Um, I think we're
kind of right now hyperfocused,
especially when kids are younger. Well,
you only can play one sport. You only
focus on one sport. In the end, you want
to let the player and the athlete just
kind of figure it out. And you might see
some thing in things in another sport.
Oh, that's interesting. All right. It's
not that it's necessarily going to apply
apples to apples, but it's always
interesting when they're doing other
things. It kind of speaks to their
athleticism, speaks to their thought
process, speaks to their mindset. So,
yeah, absolutely. I would just say even
for this generation, I would encourage
as many your the kids to play as many
sports as possible until you ultimately
have to make a decision where that's
going to be your primary focus.
>> All right, so Johnny talked about
driving home after the draft is over.
What about driving home on Thursday
night and Friday night? Can you sleep
those nights or are the wheels turning
and you're thinking about all the
possibilities? How does that go for you?
>> Yeah, you try to, but it's hard. Your
your head is just racing and spinning
and thinking about the next day. You you
get home, you try to relax, and you try
to go to bed, but I mean, honestly, it
was hard to do. Then you're up the next
day, and then you're going. So,
>> all right. So, this this gets into my
next question, Nick, because we always
ask you these things. You're a very
healthy person.
>> Everybody listening, watching, everybody
has trouble sleeping. Okay. Everybody I
talk to, trouble sleeping. What's the
Cacerio method for getting a good
night's sleep? It's the world's greatest
performance-enhancing drug. So, what's
your solution, Nick?
>> Well, probably our dog is probably the
best solution. So, our dog sleeps right
next to me. Um, I sleep on downstairs on
the couch cuz I get up super early, so I
don't want to disrupt the entire
household. But when I lay down, she's
right next to me there. So, and then we
put her music on that helps her fall
asleep, but it probably also helps me
fall asleep as well.
>> Nick, one of the one guy who had to do
something like that on Thursday night
was Kaden, and he ended up staying in
Pittsburgh for the draft. I think there
may have been one other that ended up
leaving, but he stayed. That matter to
you guys that he had, I made the
commitment to stay. I'm going to stay
and go through the process on Friday.
Did that matter to you guys that you saw
your guy being so committed that hey
that's what we saw in him on tape. We
learned that of him that he is that kind
of guy. Did that matter to you guys at
all?
>> Yeah, a small part of it. I mean
honestly that's that wasn't probably an
ideal situation because I'm sure there
was excitement and aspirations about
going the night before. But look, it's a
good example of sometimes things aren't
going to go the way that you hope or
want them to go.
>> So how do you respond? Do you just get
up and move on to the next play? do you
move on to the next day? In a small
snapshot, there's an example of he was
willing to do that. Um, probably wasn't
easy for him to do. I mean, the reality
was he wasn't going to last very long,
whether we picked him or someone else
picked him. But, uh, but yeah, I mean,
it wasn't an easy situation, but he made
the most of it. So, credit to him and,
you know, Drew Rosenhouse for sticking
it out the way that they did.
>> Did you guys see Billy Miller announce
some picks?
>> We did see that. Yes, we did. Very
impressive. They showed his highlight of
the first touchdown in the history of
the organization. 25th year. There you
go. That's very good. All right. Thanks
a lot for joining us. Good luck, Nick.